Howells family. Howells family papers (MS Am 1784-1784.13): Guide.
Howells family papers,
- VI. bMS Am 1784.11: The John Mead Howells Collection
  - B. Letters to John Mead Howells (gift)
    - Belcher, Hannah Graham. 1 letter; 1943., (6)
    - Booth, F.G. 1 letter; 1938., (7)
    - Buell, Ely. 1 letter; 1934., (8)
    - Firkins, Oscar W., 1864-1932. 1 letter; 1928., (9)
      *45M-523
    - Frear, Walter Francis, 1863-. 1 letter; 1942., (10)
    - Greenslet, Ferris, 1875-1959. 1 letter; 1928., (11)
      Copy.
    - Landale, Russell H. 1 letter; 1908., (12)
    - Lewis, Leo Rich, 1865-1945. 1 letter; 1943., (13)
    - Matteis, Maria de. 1 letter; 1929., (14)
    - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-. 1 letter; 1937., (15)
    - Poole, Ernest, 1880-1950. 1 letter; 1918., (16)
    - Punké, Edward G. 1 letter; 1930., (17)
    - Quinby, Henry Cole, 1872-1922. 1 letter; 1918., (18)
    - Salisbury, Leah. 1 letter; 1931., (19)
    - Whistler, James Abbot McNeill, 1834-1903. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (20)
      *45M-517
  - C. Letters from John Mead Howells
    Letters from John Mead Howells to various correspondents.
    - Ayer, Dana S., addressee. 2 letters; 1920., (21)
      No. 1 with a typed copy; no. 2 with two typed copies.
      *44M-114
    - Booth, F.G., addressee. 1 letter; 1938., (22)
    - Collins, Seward B., addressee. 1 letter; 1928., (23)
    - Franzen, August, addressee. 1 letter; 1907., (24)
      File copy.
    - Howells, Mildred, 1872-, addressee. 40 letters; [1893]-[1955] [n.d.]., (25)
      No. 11 by secretary.
      Many with typed copies.
      1,19: *45M-518
      2,16,20,21,39: *54M-329
      4: *44M-115
      17: *45M-322
      31: *45M-530
      14,26,36: *45M-531
      27,28,34: *45M-532
      24: *53M-96
      others: *59M-286
    - Howells, Mildred, 1872-, addressee. 3 letters; 1928 [n.d.]., (26)
    - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920, addressee. 5 letters; [1919] [n.d.]., (27)
      *59M-285
    - North, Ernest Dressel, addressee. 1 letter; 1928., (28)
    - Pennell, Joseph, 1857-1926, addressee. 1 letter; 1924., (29)
      With extra file copy.
      *44M-116
    - Pollard and Steinam, addressee. 1 letter; [n.d.]., (30)
    - Punké, Edward G., addressee. 1 letter; 1930., (31)
    - Robins, Lillian M., addressee. 1 letter; 1924., (32)
      With copy of letter from Lillian Robins to John Mead Howells.
    - Smith, Thomas Robert, 1880-1933, addressee. 1 letter; 1924., (33)
    - John Mead Howells as a child: tintype, undated., (33a)
      Possibly John Mead?
- VII. bMS Am 1784.12: Additional material
  - A. Other letters (purchase)
    - Browning, Robert, 1812-1889. 1 letter to [Moncure Daniel] Conway; 1863., (1)
    - Carter, Belle E. 1 letter to Aurelia Howells; [n.d.]., (2)
    - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910. 1 letter to the United States Congress; [ca. 1875]., (3)
    - Coe, Alice. 1 letter to Harper and brothers; 1926., (3a)
    - Cohn, James D. 1 letter to [] Mabie; 1895., (4)
    - Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907. 1 letter to George William Curtis; [n.d.]., (5)
    - Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907. 1 letter to Octavius Brooks Frothingham; [n.d.]., (6)
    - Curtis, George William, 1824-1892. 1 letter to [] Mead; 1859., (7)
    - Dalziel, D. 2 letters to John Whitmore; 1885., (8)
    - Dana, Charles Anderson, 1819-1897. 1 letter to Samuel Sidney McClure; 1890., (8a)
    - Douglas, David, 1823-1916. 1 letter to Hachette and co.; 1883., (9)
    - Douglas, David, 1823-1916. 1 letter to Osgood, McIlvaine and co.; 1891., (10)
    - Dronsart, Marie. 1 letter to David Douglas; 1889., (11)
    - Duvirer, P. 1 letter to [] Calmette; 1896., (12)
    - Fairchild, Charles. 2 letters to Joseph Wesley Harper; [1885]., (13)
      Drafts of telegrams.
    - Florimond, []. 1 letter to [Harper and Bros.];1902., (14)
    - Freeman, Mary Eleanor (Wilkins) 1852-1930. 1 letter to Hamlin Garland; 1891., (15)
    - Garfield, James Abram, pres. U.S., 1831-1881. 1 letter to William Cooper Howells; 1877., (16)
      With note from [William Cooper Howells] to [William Dean Howells].
    - Giddings, Joshua Reed, 1795-1864. 1 letter to William Cullen Bryant; 1861., (17)
    - Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1831-1908. 2 letters to Richard Watson Gilder; 1882., (18)
    - Graham, James Lorimer, 1835-1876. 1 letter to [] Huntington; 1862., (19)
    - Graham, James Lorimer, 1835-1876. 1 letter to Trübner and co.; 1862., (20)
    - Harper, Joseph Wesley, d. 1896. 3 letters to Charles Fairchild; 1885., (21)
      No. 3 with note from Charles Fairchild to William Dean Howells.
    - Hayes, Rutherford Birchard, pres. U.S., 1822-1893. 1 letter to [Ezra Bartlett] French; 1880., (22)
    - Hayes, Rutherford Birchard, pres. U.S., 1822-1893. 1 letter to A.D. Shepard; 1880., (23)
    - Hayes, Rutherford Birchard, pres. U.S., 1822-1893. 1 letter to James Russell Lowell; 1877., (23a)
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894. 1 letter to James Ripley Osgood; [n.d.]., (24)
    - Houghton Mifflin company. 1 letter to James Ripley Osgood and co.; 1881., (25)
    - Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936. 1 letter to [] Marshall; 1897., (26)
    - Lowell, James Russell, 1819-1891. 1 letter to Nathaniel Hawthorne; 1860., (27)
    - McKim, Charles Follen, 1847-1909. 1 letter to William Rutherford Mead; 1885., (28)
    - Morse, Robert McNeill, 1837-1920. 1 letter to [Samuel Wells]; 1885., (29)
    - Osgood, McIlvaine and co., London. 1 letter to David Douglas; 1891., (30)
    - Powers, Hiram, 1805-1873. 1 letter to []; 1868., (31)
    - Salvini, Alessandro. 1 letter to []; 1893., (32)
    - Sherman, John, 1823-1900. 1 letter to William Cooper Howells; 1882., (33)
    - [Smith, Roswell, 1829-1892]. 1 letter to Richard Watson Gilder; 1884., (34)
      With a note from Richard Watson Gilder to William Dean Howells.
    - Smith, Roswell, 1829-1892. 1 letter to [James Ripley] Osgood; 1882., (35)
    - Spies, August, 1855-1887. 1 letter to W.M. Salter; 1887., (36)
      Also signed by Michael Schwab and S. Fielden.
    - Stanton, Elizabeth Cobden, lady Hughes. 1 letter to (Mrs.) Moncure D. Conway; [n.d.]., (37)
    - Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903. 1 letter to William Cox Bennett; 1861., (38)
    - Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903. 1 letter to George Henry Boughton; 1861., (39)
    - Tauchnitz, [] freiherr von. 1 letter to []; 1886., (40)
      Possibly to Thomas B. Ticknor.
    - Tyler, George H. 1 letter to James Ripley Osgood; 1884., (41)
    - Warner, Charles Dudley, 1829-1900. 1 letter to [James Ripley] Osgood; 1874., (42)
    - Wheatley, J. Percival D. 1 letter to [Harper and Bros.];1895., (43)
    - Whitmore, John. 1 letter to James R. Osgood and co.; 1884., (44)
      Wilkins, Mary Eleanor, 1852-1930. See Freeman, Mary Eleanor (Wilkins) 1852-1930.
  - B. Other letters (gift)
    - Banks, Sarah. 1 letter to Harper and Bros.; 1926., (45)
    - Bartlett, Mabel L. 1 letter to Harper and Bros.; 1927., (46)
    - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910. 1 letter to James Ripley Osgood; [n.d.]., (47)
    - Collins, Seward B. 1 letter to Nannine V. Joseph; 1928., (48)
    - Fales, William H. 1 letter to Charles Henry Fiske; 1912., (49)
    - Fiske, Charles Henry, 1872-. 1 letter to William H. Fales; 1912., (50)
    - Harkins, D.H. 1 letter to Samuel Langhorne Clemens; 1875., (51)
    - Harper, Joseph Wesley, d. 1896. 1 letter to John Hay; 1880., (52)
    - Houghton Mifflin company. 1 letter to Samuel Wells; 1889., (53)
    - Jensen, Gerard Edward, 1884-. 1 letter to [Dorothy] Fiske; 1939., (54)
    - Keil, Paul L. 1 letter to Harper and Bros.; 1929., (55)
    - Montel, Denise. 1 letter to Houghton Mifflin company; 1931., (56)
    - Mookerjee, Harendra Coomar. 1 letter to Harper and Bros.; 1924., (57)
    - Punké, Edward G. 1 letter to Harper and Bros.; 1930., (58)
    - Sergel, Charles Hubbard. 1 letter to Harper and Bros.; 1924., (59)
    - Simoas, Florence A. 1 letter to Harper and Bros.; 1926., (60)
    - Willard, J.F. 1 letter to [] Lloyd; 1902., (61)
    - Wyatt, Edith Franklin, 1873-1958. 1 letter to [Booth] Tarkington; 1920., (62)
  - C. Other compositions
    - Brown, Phyllis Wyatt. W.D.H. TS. (signed); [n.p., n.d.], (63); 1s.(1p.)
    - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910. [Colonel Mulberry Sellers, inventor]. TS. (carbon copy, unsigned); [n.p., n.d.], (64); 4s.(4p.)
      A play by S.L. Clemens and W.D. Howells.
      This material was used by Clemens in The American Claimant.
      A reader notes: this is not a dramatic version of Col. Mulberry Sellers as labelled, but a dramatic version of Mark Twain (SLC's) short story "The death disk."
    - Eckfeld, E. "My sorrow that I tie..." A.MS. (signed); Dennison, Ohio, [n.d.], (65); 1s.(1p.)
    - Erskine, John, 1879-1951. William Dean Howells. TS. (unsigned); [n.p., ca. 1920], (66); 4s.(4p.)
      Publ. in The bookman (June 1920).
    - Fairley, Barker, 1887-. Selected writings of William Dean Howells, published by Random House. TS. (carbon copy, unsigned); [n.p., ca. 1950], (67); 6s.(6p.)
      Script of a radio talk broadcast by the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, 22 Oct. 1950.
    - Fréchette, Howells. [Tribute to William Dean Howells]. TS. (unsigned); [n.p., ca. 1920], (68); 1s.(1p.)
    - Henschel, Sir Georg, 1850-1934. A sea-change [or Love's stowaway]. MS.; [Leipzig, 1884], (69); 1 box.
      Orchestral score with parts for the opera by W.D. Howells and Sir Georg Henschel. In the hand of the copyist Erdmann Hartmann.
    - Henschel, Sir Georg, 1850-1934. A sea-change, or Love's stowaway. Working copy; [n.p., n.d.], (70); 2v.
      Mounted clippings from a printed text with autograph revisions by W.D. Howells.
    - [Howe, Mark Antony DeWolfe, 1864-1960]. [Tribute to William Dean Howells]. TS. (unsigned); [n.p., ca. 1920], (71); 5s.(5p.)
      With corrections in an unidentified hand.
    - Howells, Aurelia H. Paper on William Dean Howells. TS. (unsigned); [n.p., n.d.], (72); 8s.(8p.)
      Read before the Women's club at Santa Monica, Calif.
      *58M-16
    - Mead, John Noyes, 1831-1850. John Mead's journal, Harvard, 1847-1850. TS. (carbon copy, modern transcript); [n.p., n.d.], (73); 172s.(172p.)
      Edited by John Mead Howells.
      *59M-284
    - Mead, Larkin Goldsmith, 1835-1910. [Sketches: Scenes on steamer]. [n.p., 1862], (74); 1s.(1p.)
      Sketches made by Larkin Mead on his first trip to Europe.
    - Tarkington, Booth, 1869-1946. Mr. Howells. TS. (unsigned, carbon copy); [n.p., ca. 1920], (75); 9s.(9p.)
      Published in Harper's monthly magazine, (Aug. 1920) v.141, p.346-350.
    - White, William Allen, 1868-1944.; [William Dean Howells]. TS. (unsigned); [n.p., 1912], (76); 2s.(2p.)
    - [] Les remords de David. MS. (unsigned, unidentified hand); [n.p., n.d.], (77); 1s.(1p.)
      Unidentified 19th century French poem.
- VIII. bMS AM 1784.13: Additional correspondence
  Gift of Mildred Howells 1942
  Note: This material was closed until 1972, now open.
  - Howells, Elinor Gertrude (Mead) d.1910. 17 letters to Annie (Howells) Fréchette; 1864-[1897?], (1)
    Nos. 2 and 3 with a note by William Dean Howells.
  - Howells, Elinor Gertrude (Mead) d.1910. 11 letters to Aurelia H. Howells; 1863-[1879], (2)
  - Howells, Elinor Gertrude (Mead) d.1910. 1 letter to Eliza Howells; 1864, (3)
  - Howells, Elinor Gertrude (Mead) d.1910. 8 letters to Mary (Dean) Howells; 1863-1868, (4)
    No. 4 with a note by William Dean Howells.
  - Howells, Elinor Gertrude (Mead) d.1910. 2 letters to Samuel Dean Howells; [1873]-1864, (5)
  - Howells, Elinor Gertrude (Mead) d.1910. 6 letters to Victoria Mellor Howells; 1863-1882, (6)
  - Howells, Elinor Gertrude (Mead) d.1910. 12 letters to William Cooper Howells; 1864-1883, (7)
  - Howells, Elinor Gertrude (Mead) d.1910. 8 letters to the "Howells family"; 1863-[1879], (8)
    Nos. 5, 7 and 8 incomplete.
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920. 2 letters to Annie (Howells) Fréchette; 1867-1873, (9)
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920. 25 letters to Aurelia H. Howells; 1864-1917, (10)
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920. 105 letters to Elinor Gertrude (Mead) Howells; 1865-1909, (11)
    No. 2 with a letter from Larkin G. Mead.
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920. 8 letters to Joseph Alexander Howells; 1906-1911, (12)
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920. 2 letters to Mary (Dean) Howells; 1863-1867, (13)
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920. 6 letters to Victoria Mellor Howells; 1876-1882, (14)
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920. 39 letters to William Cooper Howells; 1863-1882, (15)
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1909. [Lady of the Aroostock]. MS.(unsigned); [n.p., n.d.], (16); 1s.(2p.)
    Outline of the plot in the hand of Elinor Gertrude (Mead) Howells.
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1909. 1 letter to James Ford Rhodes; 1912., (17)
    With a letter from Rhodes to Mildred Howells; 1921.
  - Howells, William Dean, 1837-1909. 2 letters to Winifred Howells; 1868., (18)